# James Watson

+1 (301)-905-8154 | 05watson.j@gmail.com | Google Scholar | Linkedin

# **Summary**

I am a quantum computing Research Fellow interested in finding tasks that quantum computers will excel at in the immediate future. My research has involved calculating & optimizing resource costs for quantum simulation algorithms for physics and chemistry; demonstrating the effectiveness of classical machine learning using quantum data; putting complexity theoretic bounds on the effectiveness of quantum algorithms; and applying tools from complexity theory to improve our understanding of physics. This broad experience makes me well-placed to tackle a range of quantum problems. I am interested in using classical computation and machine learning to speed up and improve quantum computing.

# **Academic Experience**

## Postdoctoral Research Fellow | University of Maryland, College Park | Sept 2021 - Current

- · Selected examples of research:
  - o Developed quantum algorithms for solving problems in nuclear physics & estimated resource costs.
  - o Developing software package to reduce algorithm error in Product Formula-based simulations.
  - o Machine learning applied to data from quantum data sources to efficiently predict properties.
  - o Complexity-theoretic lower bounds on the efficiency of quantum algorithms for physics problems.
- · Presented research at leading conferences in the field including QIP.
- · Mentored graduate students, interfaced with stakeholders, etc.

#### PhD (Quantum Computing) | Supervisor: Toby Cubitt | University College London | Sept 2016 - Sept 2021

- · Research in quantum computing and its relation to many-body physics.
- Guest lectured quantum algorithms courses: algorithms for linear systems and quantum simulation.
- Teaching Assistant for undergraduate mathematics & physics courses.
- · Organized multiple student conferences and seminar groups.

#### Education

#### MMath (Part III Mathematics) | University of Cambridge | Sept 2015 - Sept 2016

- · Awarded Distinction (highest possible grade).
- Thesis: The Tensor Renormalization Group for Condensed Matter Physics.
- · Courses: quantum field theory, string theory, general relativity, statistical field theory, black holes, quantum information, quantum computation.

# Bachelors (Physics) | University of Cambridge | Sept 2012 - Sept 2015

- · Awarded 1st Class degree (highest possible grade).
- Ranked in top 10 in program of +200.
- · Courses: linear algebra, differential equations., calculus, probability, quantum mechanics, electrodynamics, electromagnetism, thermodynamics, mechanics, Python, C++, numerical methods, General Relativity, Math Methods.

# **Professional Work**

# Summer Associate | Goldman Sachs | June 2015 - Aug 2015

- · Built custom models for estimating oil shipping prices based on publicly available data.
- · Provided hedging analysis for clients in commodities trading using statistical analysis techniques.
- · Monte Carlo pricing of complex over-the-counter options using GS proprietary language, Slang.

# Summer Intern | Daiwa Capital Markets | July 2014

· Spent time with trading desks and rotation through fixed income, equities, DCM and quant analysis.

#### **Awards & Honors**

- EPRSC Research Fellowship, 2017-2021.
- · Top 10 ranking in my undergraduate class at Cambridge.
- · Cambridge University Churchill Scholarship for Academic Excellence, 2013, 2014, & 2015.
- Top 5 Candidate National Physics Olympiad UK, AS-Level, 2011.

### **Additional Skills**

- · Languages: Python, MATLAB, and Mathematica.
- · Tools: Numpy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, XGBoost, Scipy, Git + Github/Gitlab, Jupyter Notebook.
- · Other: Excel, Word, Outlook, PowerPoint, and LaTeX.

## **Other Professional Activities**

- · Program Committee Member: QIP 2023, YQIS 2024
- · Conference Reviewer: QIP, TQC, STOC, QSIM, STACS, CCC, ICALP.
- · Journal Reviewer: Nature Communications, Quantum, SIAM, Foundations of Physics, CIMP.
- · Outreach for schools and women in STEM initiatives.

# **Research Papers**

#### **Published**

- The Complexity of Translationally Invariant Problems beyond Ground State Energies. J. D. Watson, J. Bausch, and S. Gharibian, 40th International Symposium on Theoretical Aspects of Computer Science (STACS 2023), 254, (2023). doi:10.4230/LIPIcs.STACS.2023.54
- · *Uncomputably Complex Renormalisation Group Flows.* J. D. Watson, E. Onorati, & T. S. Cubitt, Nature Communications, 13(1). (2022). doi:10.1038/s41467-022-35179-4
- Computational complexity of the ground state energy density problem. J. D. Watson, & T. S. Cubitt, Proceedings of the 54th Annual ACM SIGACT Symposium on Theory of Computing. (2022). doi:10.1145/3519935.3520052
- \*Uncomputability of phase diagrams. J. Bausch, T. S. Cubitt, & J. D. Watson, Nature Communications, 12(1), (2021). doi:10.1038/s41467-020-20504-6

#### **Preprints**

- Polynomial-Time Classical Simulation of Noisy IQP Circuits after Constant Depth. J. Rajakumar, J. D. Watson, Y.-K. Liu. arXiv:2403.14607 [Under Review: FOCS]
- · Quantum Algorithms for Simulating Nuclear Effective Field Theories. J. D. Watson, J. Bringewatt, A. F. Shaw, A. Childs, Z. Davoud, A. Gorshkov. arXiv:2312.05344 [Under Review: PRX]
- \*Provably Efficient Learning of Phases of Matter via Dissipative Evolutions. E. Onorati, C. Rouze, D. Stilck Franca, and J. D Watson. arXiv:2311.07506 [Under Review: Annales Henri Poincaré]

- \*\*Efficient learning of ground and thermal states within phases of matter. E. Onorati, C. Rouze, D. Stilck Franca, and J. D Watson. arXiv:2301.12946 [Accepted: Nature Communications]
- The Complexity of Approximating Critical Points of Quantum Phase Transitions. J. D. Watson and J. Bausch. arXiv:2105.13350 [Under Review: PRX]
- · Detailed Analysis of Circuit-to-Hamiltonian Mappings. J. D. Watson. arXiv:1910.01481

#### Soon to be Released (Manuscripts available on request)

- · Nearly Optimal Computation of Time-Evolved Expectation Values using Trotterization with Richardson Extrapolation. J. D. Watson and J. Watkins.
- *Improved quantum supremacy using Gibbs sampling from O(1)-local Hamiltonians.* J. D. Watson and J. Rajakumar.
- \*Denotes papers ordered alphabetically where I am primary contributor.
- \*\*Denotes papers ordered alphabetically where I am joint primary contributor.

# **Supervising and Mentoring Experience**

Joel Rajakumar - PhD student, University of Maryland

**Andrew Zheng** – Undergraduate Research Projects, University of Maryland.

**David Kong** – Undergraduate Research Projetcs, University of Maryland.

# **Selected Conference Talks**

- · QIP 2024 (Taipei, Taiwan) "Efficient Learning of Phases of Matter"
- TQC 2023 (Averio, Portugal) "Efficient learning of ground and thermal states within phases of matter"
- ECT\* 2023 "Nuclear and particle physics on a quantum computer: Where do we stand now?" (Trento, Italy) "Quantum Algorithms for Simulating Nuclear Physics"
- VTQ-QIS Workshop 2023 (Arlington, Virginia) "Efficient learning of ground and thermal states within phases of matter"
- · Young Innovators Conference 2022 (IQC, Waterloo), "Complexity and Computability in Physics"
- STOC 2022 (Rome, Italy) "The Computational Complexity of the Ground State Energy Density Problem"
- ML and Quantum for Nuclear Physics 2022 (Seattle, US), "Quantum Algorithms for Simulating Nuclear Physics"
- QIP 2022 Plenary Talk (Caltech, US) "Complexity in the Thermodynamic Limit: The Ground State Energy Density Problem"
- Workshop on Combinatorial Reconfiguration, ICALP 2021 (Virtual) "The Complexity of Translationally Invariant Problems beyond Ground State"
- QIP 2020 (Shenzhen, China): "The Uncomputability of Phase Diagrams".
- Quantum Simulation and Computation, 2019 (ICMAT, Madrid): "The Uncomputability of Phase Diagrams".
- **Quantum Roundabout 2018** (Nottingham, UK): "Computational Complexity of the Ground State Energy Density Problem" **Runner up prize for best talk**.